### **ROSALIND MARY BURGESS**

Field View, 8 Rectory Close, Warmington, Banbury, Oxon OX17 1DL

Tel/Fax: 01295 690457 Mob: 07984 034778

E-mail: rosalindburgess@googlemail.com

A high calibre sales and marketing professional with a successful track record in technical sales, developing and closing business opportunities in the UK and export markets. A people person with good analytical ability and over 20 years' experience of managing internal staff and overseas distribution channels. An excellent communicator with a history of achievements and a positive "can do" attitude to problem solving with many different cultures. Strength in building partnerships; ambitious, determined and energetic with a great desire for results.

### **CAREER HISTORY**

# March 09 Wood & Douglas Ltd, Tadley, - Date

Wood & Douglas is the UK's leading designer and manufacturer of wireless solutions for data, video and voice communication. Privately owned, Wood & Douglas' major customers include the utilities, transport, oil and gas, military and security forces in the UK, US, France, Denmark; plus major OEM customers such as Siemens, Draeger, Saab.

## Business Development Manager - Utilities & Export

- Responsibility for developing interest in and closing orders with UK electricity companies for a product to resolve major issues for inter-tripping surrounding BT21CN
- Management of the utility accounts, electricity, water and gas and associated cos., involving major presentations to new contacts, quoting and closing business
- Search for and subsequent management of engineering companies and system integrators, quoting and closing sales
- Management and updating of Achilles UVDB and registration with Achilles Link Up database. Daily review of OJEU tenders. Replying to call for expressions of interest in restricted tenders
- Search for new contacts in the UK and overseas, establishing contact, quoting and developing sales. A great deal of "missionary work" completed
- Management of existing distribution and system integrators overseas
- Initiating contacts in new vertical market sectors in UK and overseas, e.g. aquaculture, transport, OEM radio users in Scandinavia, developing relationships and business opportunities

# 2005 – 09 Elpro Technologies, Brisbane, Australia part of US\$ 5 bn Cooper Industries

Elpro is the world leader in the supply of wireless data modems and telemetry modules for the monitoring and control of processes in industrial applications. Acquired by MTL Instruments Group, 2007, subsequently bought by Cooper Industries, 2008

## Sales Network Manager, Europe

- Responsibility for the research, selection, appointment, training and management of 30 distributors throughout Europe and their achievement of annual sales budgets
- 11 new channels appointed and trained in the past 2 years
- Management of the European HQ at a central office near Banbury
- Exceeded budget requirements and achieved bonus target on territory providing 30% of Company turnover, £1.5m in sales

Increased company profile in the direct distribution and OEM market

# 2002 - 03 Norbar Ltd., Banbury

A family run manufacturing company supplying OEMs and dealers worldwide with torque tools, testing equipment and calibration services. Customers include Wuerth, Germany, Peugeot, France. Employs 200 staff in the UK, Australia, Singapore and the USA. Turnover £20m

### Sales Co-ordinator

Order processing, customer service and foreign language duties.

## 2001 - 02 International Summer School, Oxford Brookes University

MSc placements at British and overseas universities are dependent upon successful grades obtained at Summer School which is established to provide 6 weeks intensive English language study to undergraduates, postgraduates and foreign teaching staff

# Manager, International Summer School

Managed 8 office staff providing administrative and social programme services to 200 students and supported the Academic Director and 30 academic staff

## 1997 - 2001 RMB International Sales and Marketing, Banbury

### 2003 - 2005

Working as a consultant providing sales and marketing services and foreign language capability to UK and overseas companies.

### Consultant

- Contract work for Real World, a provider of sales training packages, telemarketing of the company's services and making appointments for the company directors
- Sales support, strategic marketing and foreign language skills to company sales managers, engineers, Sales Director and Divisional MD of Eliza Tinsley plc., (turnover £70m) prior to and during overseas exhibition
- Undertook market report in French for French food manufacturer and proposed sales and marketing strategy for their product launch in the UK.
- PR and stand management including sales services to a leading UK importer of food processing machinery in Ireland
- Various commercial translating and interpreting projects

# 1996 - 97 Anilam Electronics, Newport Pagnell

Manufacturer of electronics for the machine tool industry, based in Miramar, Florida, USA. And a subsidiary of the German Heidenhain Group, the world leading supplier, employing 6,000 staff.

# **Export Sales Manager**

Reporting to the company President based in Florida, but working out of the UK office, managing sales through a distributor network in Europe, India and South Africa and OEM business.

- Achieved and exceeded budgeted annual sales of £800k
- Reviewed markets and appointed new distributors
- Formulated successful sales and marketing strategy to increase market share
- Introduced CNC retrofit control and obtained first order in Finland's "silicon valley"
- Trained distributor sales staff to demonstrate new CNC control

# 1983 - 96 ELE International Ltd., Hemel Hempstead

The world leader in the manufacture and supply of civil engineering, agronomics and environmental laboratories and field equipment. Formerly a subsidiary of Mowlem plc, South West Water plc., (Viridor), now owned by the US Danaher Corp., ELE supplied 10,000 product lines to 150 countries, turning over £40m

# Export Sales Manager/Project Manager

Managed sales in South America and Europe plus projects funded by the international lending agencies in the UK, Europe and USA. Sold through a distributor network and direct to end-users, using French, German and Spanish language skills to facilitate business deals.

- Achieved annual sales of £2m for 3 company divisions across 10,000 line items
- Reviewed market performance against budget, sought and appointed new distributors
- Obtained market intelligence on medium and long-term projects by visits to the World Bank, UN, ODA and delivered £300k annually in direct sales to these agencies
- Convinced British government to agree to medium-term bi-lateral funding to supply civil engineering laboratory departments in Iraqi universities
- Negotiated projects of £750k (Iraq Universities of Mosul and Mustansiriya, British credit line) and £500k (Pakistan, UNDP funds)
- Implemented strategy for first phase of World Bank education project, YOK I in Turkey for £1.2m with additional orders of £5.2m, YOK II
- Achieved sales of £1m in South America and delivered highest value agronomics order for the area at the time of £162k with repeat orders of £91k. The first project of its type in the country for 10 years receiving World Bank funds
- Delivered £600k in sales to the emerging East European markets through direct negotiation with international contractors and government laboratories via market development strategy with repeat orders
- Managed multi-million £/\$ projects from the tender stage through to installation of equipment including all commercial negotiations and technical discussions
- Visited consultants and project specifiers in the UK and overseas, obtaining market intelligence data and getting products specified in tender documents
- Trained distributor sales staff and end-users on hardware and software.
- Conducted presentations to high level Trade Missions often with DTI sponsorship, e.g. Minister for Works, Madagascar, in French
- Ran product seminars and business meetings, deputised for Company Chairman
- Organised and manned exhibitions in the UK and overseas

# 1981 - 83 Access Equipment/Aldep International Ltd., Hemel Hempstead

### Export Sales Controller/Administration Manager

Access Equipment manufactured hydraulic lifts and aluminium scaffolding. The MD of Access left and set up Aldep and I was headhunted to join a start-up team. Aldep sourced its equipment from Germany and I was interpreter during negotiations

## 1979 - 81 Holt Whitney, Birmingham/Meridien Intl Credit Corp., London

# Export Executive/Credit Assistant

Holt Whitney, an established confirming house was bought by much larger Meridien Intl Credit Corp.(client billing £6m per month), part of the Wade Adams group

# **EDUCATION AND QUALIFICATIONS**

**1989 – 90** Luton College of Further Education, Institute of Linguists: Spanish and Italian.

- **1981** Sutton Coldfield College of Further Education: Export Marketing (Part One).
- **1975 79** University of Coventry, B.A. (Hons) Modern Languages: French, German, Spanish.
- **1968 75** TP Riley School, Bloxwich, West Midlands, 9 GCE O Levels and 2 GCE A Levels

### **TRAINING**

Time Management, Export Management and Marketing courses run by E.C. Rollinson Co. Ltd; Sales Presentation Skills seminars; Computer training courses on ACT Data Management software, Microsoft Office, Access and Excel, CEDAR and Goldmine.

## **PERSONAL INTERESTS**

Watercolour painting, ballet, dance, keep fit, skiing, theatre, live music, cooking, reading, National Trust, travel and the "big outdoors".

**Rosalind Burgess**